Good morning. Good ערב שבת שובה. Erev Shabbos Shuvah. So today's דף,
daf, we're about a דף daf ahead, so we're going to call
today's דף daf as כ"ח. chaf ches. We pick up in the
middle of כ"ז עמוד ב' chaf zayin amud bais and we're up
to מתיב רבא. masiv rava. We are finally wrapping up the סוגיא
sugya about the pile of unspecified funds that goes towards an עולה
olah in the case when even though the three קרבנות korbanot were
going to come from it of the נזיר, nazir, the שלמים, shelamin,
the חטאת, chatas, and the עולה, olah, this pile of unspecified funds
goes towards the עולה. olah. And we just went through a whole
long discussion about whether that is a הלכה halacha limited to money
or does it apply to other things, things like, I don't know,
beams of wood, bars of gold, bars of precious metal,
animals without a blemish that it's going to take time to redeem.
But even in the context that it applied to money, we had
been saying that that would include so there's that debate. Maybe it
applies only to money or maybe it applies to everything, even things
that would take time to liquidate. But even in the context that
it applied only to money, we didn't make it literally money. We
said things that also could similarly be liquidated quickly and easily. So
the argument was that animals with a blemish, which because of their
קדושה kedusha you would not have to wait to sell and presumably
would be easy to transfer into cash, had a very ready market
and did not need time to assess their value and so on,
that would be in the cash category. So that's the background and
now we're questioning whether that's true, whether maybe animals even with a
blemish should not be in this cash category and should not have
this הלכה halacha that an unspecified if you sanctify three cows, even
though the קרבנות korbanot of a נזיר nazir cannot come from cows,
if you sanctify them and then the guy dies or the נזירות
nezirus is nullified, that you cannot then that this הלכה halacha that
they the קדושה kedusha eventually goes for an עולה olah might not
apply, assuming it applies only to money. Would it apply to these
animals
that have a blemish and are not the animals that can be
used? So that's the context. So we're going to have one more
attempt to prove that issue and then that'll take us to the
משנה mishnah on the next דף. daf. So we pick up with
מתיב רבא, masiv rava, the middle of כ"ז עמוד ב', chaf zayin
amud bais, it's right smack in the middle there, middle of the
line about exactly halfway down. Line starts with דמי הני מעות. d'may
hani maos. So מתיב רבא. masiv rava. I think that's the wrong
גמרא. gemara. רבא Rava asked, קרבנו, korbano, בקרבנו הוא יוצא ואינו יוצא
בקרבן אביו. bekorbano hu yotzei v'eino yotzei bekorban aviv. So the פסוק
pasuk is a פסוק pasuk that says that this is a general
teaching about the הלכה halacha about a קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, that
a חטאת chatas has to be only for the person and for
the sin that it was sanctified for, right? That's an idea that
we've been consistently repeating, which is why when something's sanctified for חטאת
chatas cannot itself be used, it has to let die. There's nothing
else to be done. A חטאת chatas is very specific to the
person and to the sin. And again to remind you, though, there
is this other strange הלכה halacha by a נזיר, nazir, which we've
referenced and we're going to see again, which is that, however, the
an interesting sort of contrast to this is a father sanctifies some
animals or some money, let's not say animals, some money, and then
he's a נזיר nazir and then he dies. If his son accepts
נזירות nezirus after the father's death with the express intention of using
that money to pay for his קרבנות, korbanot, for his קרבנות, korbanot,
he actually is allowed to sort of reassign this undefined pile of
money towards his קרבן. korban. So that's another interesting application including the
חטאת. chatas. But that's an application of this idea of this pile
of unspecified funds that have been sanctified. So on the one hand,
we say normally it goes towards an עולה. olah. On the other
hand, if the son, after the father has died, accepts נזירות nezirus
for the purpose of using, with the sort of stipulation of using
this money, he's allowed to do that. Okay, so there's like a
case, an interesting case where money can be used towards another person.
But the basic idea is specifically when you're dealing with specified חטאת
chatas that it can only be for that person for that sin.
So now we're going to quote a ברייתא braita that is that
really directly spells all of this out, everything we've been assuming. So
it's a very nice and convenient ברייתא braita to fill in that
to clarify that point. And it's going to be used also for
our discussion about again whether animals are in the same category as
unspecified funds. So let's take a look. So מתיב רבא, masiv rava,
so רבא Rava asked, קרבנו. korbano. So it says that the whole
פסוק pasuk is what's the whole פסוק? pasuk? נפש כי תחטא nefesh
ki techeta if אם im נפש כי תחטא nefesh ki techeta if
a soul sins, so this is by the פרשה parsha by a
חטאת, chatas, והביא קרבנו, v'heivi korbano, he should bring his קרבן, korban,
שעירת עזים, seirat izim, this goat, על חטאתו אשר חטא, al chattato
asher chata, for the sin that he has sinned. Okay, so a
person has to bring a sin offering, his קרבן korban for his
sin that he has sinned. So that's all very specific to the
person and the sin. So let's take a look. Okay, so קרבנו.
korbano. So it says בקרבנו be-korbano יוצא ואינו יוצא בקרבנו של אביו.
yotze ve-eino yotze be-korbano shel aviv. It has to be his קרבן,
korban, not his father's. So while there's this idea of this unspecified
pile of money you use his father's for נזירות, nezirot, when it's
talking about a חטאת chatat and specified and not נזירות nezirot and
so on, only his, cannot use his father's. His father sanctified an
animal for חטאת, chatat, his father died, he doesn't get to use
it for his חטאת. chatat. יכול לא יצא בקרבן אביו ובהמה שהפריש,
yachol lo yetze be-korban aviv ve-behemah she-hifrish,
maybe he does not fulfill his obligation with a sacrifice of his
father's if his father actually sanctified a specific animal, אפילו מן הקל
על הקל מן החמור על החמור, afilu min ha-kal al ha-kal min
ha-chamur al ha-chamur, even if it's for the same type of a
thing. His father did a light sin so he's going to use
it for light, it can't be that light if you're bringing a
חטאת, chatat, it's at least a חייב כרת. chayav kares. But okay,
or his father did a very weighty sin and he's going to
use it for weighty. So even if he keeps it in the
same category, fine, that's if he, he can't do that when it's
actually been sanctified, the specific animal has been sanctified. That we get.
שהרי אין אדם מגלח על בהמת אביו בנזירות, she-harei ein adam megalayach
al behemat aviv be-nezirot, because even in נזירות nezirot where there's this
idea that a guy can use his father's money, that's only by
money, but it doesn't apply if his father actually sanctified the animals.
It's only in an unspecified pile of money. So that we get,
like even by נזירות nezirot you can't use it once the animal's
been sanctified. אבל, aval, but let me nevertheless suggest that יוצא במעות
שהפריש אביו, אפילו מן החמור על הקל או מן הקל על החמור.
yotze be-maot she-hifrish aviv afilu min ha-chamur al ha-kal o min ha-kal
al ha-chamur, Maybe if the father put aside money, not an animal,
and said "I am sanctifying this money to use towards my sin
offering that I'm obligated in," and then the father died. So it's
just money, it's not an animal yet. So maybe it's not so
limited. Now on the other hand, it is specifically a חטאת. chatat.
Until now the more flexibility that we've seen by the נזיר nazir
and the unspecified money is when it's like all the קרבנות korbanot
are coming from it, not one specific one. But nevertheless, maybe there's
an idea that funds are a little bit more reassignable. So maybe
if the father sanctified a pile of money for his חטאת chatat
and died, maybe the son can use it for the son's חטאת.
chatat. Yes, did Sam press...?
Did you skip or did I just miss the first section?
Oh, did I skip?
Oh, I'm sorry, I skipped. I skipped, I skipped to the later
קרבן, korban, I'm sorry. Okay, let's do it again. Thank you very
much.
Very hard to understand a ברייתא Braita inside out out of different
order.
I apologize, we're reading it בסירוגין. be-sirogin. Okay, we'll try again. מתיב
רבה, motive Rabbah, קרבנו. korbano. Thank you for catching that Sam. בקרבנו
הוא יוצא be-korbano hu yotzei, ואינו יוצא בקרבן אביו. ve-eino yotzei be-korban
aviv, יכול לא יצא בקרבן של אביו שהפריש מן הקל על החמור.
yachol lo yetze be-korban shel aviv she-hifrish min ha-kal al ha-chamur. Thank
you. So first we start with even a more extreme case, that
you maybe I get you can't use the father if he set
aside a קרבן korban for from a lighter category of sin and
you're going to use it for a weightier category of sin, או
מן החמור על הקל, o min ha-chamur al ha-kal, from a weighty
to a lighter category, meaning then clearly it's, it's really a lot
of change in terms of the identity of the קרבן. korban. אבל,
aval, maybe יוצא בקרבן שהפריש אביו מן הקל על הקל מן החמור
על החמור, yotze be-korban she-hifrish aviv min ha-kal al ha-kal min ha-chamur
al ha-chamur, but maybe I could say if you keep it within
the same category of sin a person could use his father's חטאת.
chatat. תלמוד לומר, קרבנו. talmud lomar korbano, No, that's why it says
קרבנו, korbano. his. Very specific. קרבנו, korbano, it says it twice. בקרבנו
הוא יוצא ואינו יוצא בקרבנו של אביו. be-korbano hu yotze ve-eino yotze
be-korbano shel aviv. It's
only yours, not your father's, even if it's in the same category.
יכול לא יצא בקרבן אביו ובהמה שהפריש אפילו מן הקל על הקל
מן החמור על החמור, yachol lo yetze be-korban aviv ve-behemah she-hifrish afilu
min ha-kal al ha-kal min ha-chamur al ha-chamur, fine, I get it.
Even if it's within the same category, light sin to light sin
or weighty to weighty, you can't use the animal, a guy can't
use an animal that his father sanctified as a חטאת. chatat. It's
not his חטאת, chatat, it's his father's חטאת. chatat. I get it.
Okay, but שהרי אין אדם מגלח על בהמת אביו בנזירות, she-harei ein
adam megalayach al behemat aviv be-nezirot, because even by נזירות nezirot where
somebody can use his father's money, he can't use his father's animal.
Animal already has a very concrete, the identity has been very concretized,
very specific, and cannot be reassigned to the son. That I get.
אבל, יוצא במעות aval yotzei bema'ot. שהפריש אביו she-hifrish aviv, אפילו מן
החמור על הקל או מן הקל על החמור, afilu min ha-chamur al
ha-kal o min ha-kal al ha-chamur. but maybe money, maybe that is
more reassignable. So if his father sanctified a pile of money for
his father's חטאת chatat and then the father dies, maybe the son
can use it for the son's חטאת chatat and maybe even in
a different category, maybe even for a lighter sin or a weightier
sin. Okay, because maybe money is reassignable. Okay, now how do I
get this idea that money is reassignable? שהרי, she-harei, I mean that's
what we've been dealing with until now. A pile of money has
a certain flexibility. And in the case of a father's קרבן, korban,
שהרי אדם מגלח על מעות אביו בנזירות, she-harei adam megalayach al maot
aviv be-nezirot, בזמן שהן סתומים ולא בזמן שהן מפורשים, be-zman she-hen stumim
ve-lo be-zman she-hen meforashim, because a person can use his father's money
if his father died and his father set aside money for the
נזירות, nezirot, the son can use it for the son's נזירות nezirot
if the son accepts the נזירות nezirot afterwards. So you see that
at least when you're dealing with a pile of money, there is
a possibility to reassign. So maybe by a חטאת chatat the same
would be true. Now there is of course a difference, the difference
the ברייתא Braita already told you, is the גמרא Gemara here is
because even reassigning the pile of money from the father, it's only
when that is סתומים, stumim, when it is non-specified,
when it's a pile that's going to go some of it to
a חטאת, chatat, some of it to an עולה, olah, some of
it to a שלמים. shelamim. So that gives it this more malleability
because its identity is still a little bit unclarified, right even if
all three קרבנות, korbanot, it's still not very specific. If the father
set aside a pile of money and said this is for my
חטאת chatas for my נזיר, nazir, this is for my שלמים shlamim
for my נזיר, nazir, the son cannot use it. It's only בזמן
שהם סתומין, bizman sheheim stumin, not בזמן שהם מפורשין. bizman sheheim meforashin.
So even this ability to reassign money is only unspecified funds. Okay
once it's specified you can't. So even that comparison to a חטאת
chatas is weak, because the חטאת chatas says the father set aside
money for as the father's חטאת chatas and now the son wants
to use it. That's מפורשין. meforashin. But nevertheless the ברייתא braisa is
saying, since we find cases where money can be reassigned from father
to son, maybe that should be possible by חטאת chatas money, not
in a נזיר nazir case, simply use the father's חטאת chatas money,
let the son use it for his חטאת. chatas. תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar, קרבנו, korbano, again we're going to learn from the repetition of
the use קרבנו korbano and the specific your קרבן, korban, his
קרבן, korban, בקרבנו be-korbano הוא יוצא, yotzei no sorry, even when we're
just dealing with money, you can only the guy can you can
only bring it with your קרבן korban ואינו יוצא yotzei בקרבן אביו,
a person cannot use his father's קרבן korban even money that his
father sanctified, the person cannot the son cannot reassign for his קרבן
korban for a חטאת. chatas. This is only a הלכה halacha by
נזיר, nazir, it is not a הלכה halacha by חטאת, chatas, חטאת
chatas has to be very specifically yours. Cannot have started with the
father's and so on. Now, יכול לא יצא במעות שהפריש אביו אפילו
מן הקל על הקל ומן החמור על החמור. yakhol lo yeitzei be-maot
she-hifrish aviv afilu min ha-kal al ha-kal u-min ha-chamur al ha-chamur. Fine,
I get it that you cannot use money that the father set
aside, even if or I think they take out the word אפילו,
afilu, hold on. שהפריש אביו, no it is אפילו afilu yes, it
says מן הקל על הקל ומן החמור על החמור. min ha-kal al
ha-kal u-min ha-chamur al ha-chamur. I get that the son cannot reuse
his father's money even keeping it within similar categories, right, even you
know even if the categories are kept the same and even if
it's just money, the son cannot reuse it, אבל יוצא בקרבן שהפריש
לעצמו מן הקל על החמור ומן החמור על הקל. aval yotzei be-korban
she-hifrish le-atzmo min ha-kal al ha-chamur u-min ha-chamur al ha-kal. So what
we've now done is we've said there's no way you can use
somebody else's חטאת, chatas, even a guy's father and you say well
I inherit him you know and maybe to some degree we think
the son's a continuation of the father, so that's why we're giving
the example of the father, because even though that's the least break
in terms of a sense of ownership, okay, and even if it
just starts off as money and not as an animal, there's no
way somebody can use somebody else's חטאת, chatas, even their father's, even
just money, even if it's and once it's sanctified for a particular
person cannot be used for another person. Okay we got that. Okay
now, how about using your own money for your own חטאת chatas
but for sin number one and reassigning it to sin number two?
How about that? So that's not going to be the פסוק pasuk
of קרבנו, korbano, that's going to be the פסוק pasuk of חטאתו.
chatato. It has to be very sin-specific.
Okay and even if the guy ate חלב chelev twice?
Yes. So well let's take a look. That's okay. So maybe that's
different. Okay so
that might actually might work. Okay so anyway,
so אבל, aval, maybe you should fulfill your
obligation בקרבן שהפריש לעצמו מן הקל על הקל ומן החמור על החמור,
be-korban she-hifrish le-atzmo min ha-kal al ha-kal u-min ha-chamur al ha-chamur, maybe
even if we switch degrees, you know as long as you're keeping
it within your קרבנות, korbanot, your sins, maybe that's okay. תלמוד לומר
קרבנו על חטאתו, talmud lomar korbano al chatato, your קרבן korban for
your sin, or his literally for his sin. עד שיהא קרבנו לשום
חטאתו, ad she-yehei korbano le-shum chatato, his קרבן korban has to be
for his sin, the specific sin, it has to be sin-specific.
Fine, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, let's try to make it
better. נו יכול לא יצא בבהמה שהפריש לעצמו מן הקל על הקל
ומן החמור על החמור, nu yakhol lo yeitzei be-vehemah she-hifrish le-atzmo min
ha-kal al ha-kal u-min ha-chamur al ha-chamur, maybe you're not you don't
fulfill your obligation with an animal you separated for yourself, maybe if
you keep it even within the category, even from light to light
or from weighty to weighty, or אפילו, afilu, hold on let me
just get this
גרסא girsa here,
okay,
so take out the word אפילו. afilu. מן הקל על החמור ומן
החמור על הקל, min ha-kal al ha-chamur u-min ha-chamur al ha-kal, okay,
so or you can't go from and you can't maybe stay within
categories and certainly you wouldn't be able to go to different categories
from yourself from light to weighty or from weighty to light, so
you can't reassign your own קרבן korban from one type of sin
to the other even within the same type of category. שכן אם
הפריש בהמה על חלב והביא על דם או על דם והביא על
חלב שהרי לא מעל ולא כיפר. she-ken im hifrish behemah al chelev
ve-heivi al dam o al dam ve-heivi al chelev she-harei lo ma-al
ve-lo kipeir.
It says because here's why you can't reassign from one sin to
the next. I get for your own קרבן korban you cannot reassign
from one sin to the next even within a category, because let's
take חלב chelev and דם. dam. חלב chelev and דם dam are
similar categories, א' הן שניהם בחוץ, alef hen sheneihem be-chutz, ב' הן
שניהם כרת, bet hen sheneihem kares, so they're the same category, okay?
So I get why you can't reassign from your own sin from
one to the next, because I'll give I'll show you how a
קרבן korban for one sin doesn't work for the others. Let's say
I went ahead and I sanctified this animal as a קרבן על,
korban al, what did it say the case was? והביא על דם
הפריש בהמה על חלב והביא על דם או
על דם והביא על חלב. ve-heivi al dam hifrish behemah al chelev
ve-heivi al dam o al dam ve-heivi al chelev. Oh it goes
either way. שהרי לא מעל ולא כיפר. Sheharei lo ma'al velo kipher.
Let's say I went ahead and I took this animal that I
had sanctified for חלב. chelev. Okay? And I went ahead and I
slaughtered it and said I'm going to bring this animal for my
קרבן Korban for דם. dam. Okay? Now, if I tried to go
ahead and do that, I would not be מועל. mo'el. The reason
I wouldn't be מועל, mo'el, I mean, this sort of is like,
it's sort of trying to prove what we just said but it
also assumes what we just said. The reason it would not be
מעילה, me'ila, a misuse of הקדש, hekdesh, is because it would not
actually successfully have reassigned it. Since I cannot reassign it to a
different sin, right, I have not misused הקדש, hekdesh, right? A misuse
of הקדש, hekdesh, I mean, in a way I've wasted הקדש, hekdesh,
it's true, I slaughtered it and it didn't serve any purpose, although
תוספות Tosafot does raise an interesting question, which is let's say I
have this animal for חלב chelev and I try to bring it
על הדם al hadam and I don't get to use it for
דם, dam, am I still יוצא yotzei for חלב? chelev? Right? Has
my attempt to reassign it for דם, dam, you know, if maybe
if I do it שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, if I slaughter it
as an עולה, olah, it doesn't work, it doesn't work, but I'm
slaughtering it as a חטאת, chatat, it is a חטאת, chatat, but
just for a different sin, maybe it still works for its original
purpose. Okay, that's an interesting question.
What's פיגול? pigul? Does that have to do with?
No, let's yeah, פיגול pigul has to do with כוונה. kavana. We're
not dealing with פיגול. pigul. Oh, but כוונה kavana of the wrong
time and yeah, that's no, this is שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. This
is שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, it's not פיגול. pigul. Okay. So,
so that's an interesting question. It was a חלב chelev one and
I slaughtered it for דם, dam, maybe I'm still יוצא yotzei for
חלב. chelev. That's really interesting. But let's bracket that for a second.
Certainly I'm not יוצא yotzei for דם. dam. That's what we just
have asserted. I cannot reassign it. Because I cannot reassign it, it's
not מעילה. me'ila. מעילה me'ila is only when I essentially go ahead
and steal it, take it for my own use, benefit from it,
something that takes it down. Now, if I go ahead and I
destroy הקדש, hekdesh, I take my animal that is an עולה olah
that I sanctified and I just shoot it, okay, that is not
מעילה. me'ila. Okay? It's I'm destroying קדשים kodashim but it's not מעילה.
me'ila. I've wasted money that's הקדש hekdesh but it's not מעילה. me'ila.
So this animal, if I haven't succeeded in using it for a
wrong purpose, which I haven't because I can't reassign חלב chelev to
דם, dam, I haven't done מעילה. me'ila. Okay, so it says שהרי
לא מעל ולא כיפר. Sheharei lo ma'al velo kipher. I didn't do
מעילה me'ila because, you know, and not just and, sort of like,
because I did not achieve atonement, because I was not able to
reassign it to a different purpose. אבל, aval, maybe I would still
say, so that we get, we get like you can't reassign an
animal. Okay, now again, that didn't really prove it, it more sort
of assumed it, but okay, we get you can't reassign an animal
for a חטאת. chatat. אבל, Aval, nevertheless,
where are we, אבל יוצא במעות. Aval yotzei bema'ot, Again, maybe though
your own money, we just said you can't use your father's קרבן,
Korban, certainly not an animal but even not money.
But maybe your own money you can reassign. אבל Aval, יוצא במעות,
maybe you could fulfill your obligation with money שהפריש לעצמו shehephrish le'atzmo
מן הקל לקל ומן החמור לחמור, min hakal lakal umin hachamur lachamur,
and especially if you keep within the same category. You set aside
money for חלב, chelev, maybe you get to use it for דם.
dam. Okay? מן החמור לחמור מן הקל לקל, Min hachamur lachamur min
hakal lakal, and maybe even more, maybe you can even use it
from different categories.
Okay. שכן, Sheken, now what would be the logic that you should
be able to reassign money?
שכן אם הפריש לעצמו מעות מן החלב והביא על הדם על הדם
והביא על החלב שהרי מעל וכיפר. Sheken im hephrish le'atzmo ma'ot min
hachelev vehevi al hadam al hadam vehevi al hachelev sheharei ma'al vekipher.
Ah, because by money, what would happen by money? And here actually
it is going to demonstrate why it should work. Because since by
money you do do מעילה. me'ila. Now, how do we know that?
Because if I had this pile of for a חלב chelev money,
right, let's say, and I went ahead and I took it and
I picked it up, my own pile of money but that I
sanctified for חלב, chelev, and I picked it up for the sake
of using it for דם, dam, so that act of picking it
up is like an act sort of of like of גניבה. gneiva.
Okay? That's sort of, and that very act itself should basically, and
once you say that I've performed מעילה, me'ila, so maybe the effect
of performing מעילה me'ila should succeed in taking it out of הקדש
hekdesh because the act of מעילה me'ila has the effect of taking
it out of הקדש. hekdesh. And therefore, maybe I should be able
to therefore now reassign. Now, that doesn't really mean the money can
be reassigned. What it might mean is I might be able to
violate the קדושה, kedusha, desanctify it and then reuse it. So it's
not exactly reassigning. So let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות
Tosafot explains this a little better. So תוספות Tosafot says like this,
he says, I'm finding it, here, it's in the middle of על
חטאתו al chatato
and it's where like about 8-10 lines down, there's a ו vav
or ז zayin in a bracket, ז, zayin, it says הכי גרסינן,
hachi garsinan, okay?
So the difference that you have to know here, and part of
what I bracketed before, was that מעילה me'ila occurs only בשוגג. beshogeg.
If somebody willfully does
it.
It would be מעילה במזיד Me'ila be'mezid but it would not be
a קרבן מעילה Korban Me'ila and it would not change the status
of the object. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says like this: הכי גרסינן
שאין מעל וכיפר שהמעות אין בהם קדושת הגוף. Hachi garshinan she'ein mo'al
ve'chiper she'hame'ot ein bahem kedushat haguf. Another point that I also have
not mentioned was that one of the reasons it's also easier to
do מעילה Me'ila with a money than with an animal is that
something that is only sanctified for its funds, the thing itself is
not intrinsically going to be used in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Basically, the purpose of this thing is to use the proceeds to
buy the object that you're actually going to use, whether the object
is a קרבן Korban or the object is a beam that's going
to be built into the ceiling. Okay, so when the thing itself
is going to be used, that's קדושת הגוף. Kedushat HaGuf. When it's
going to be sold and the proceeds are going to be used,
that's not קדושת הגוף. Kedushat HaGuf. Okay,
that's only that's only by you know what is it? קדושת דמים.
Kedushat Damim. That's only its value is sanctified. So it's also when
you this idea that when you do מעילה Me'ila something loses its
קדושה, Kedusha, that's only by קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim. If something is
intrinsically sanctified, if I've got a קרבן, Korban, I've got an animal
that I sanctified as an עולה, Ola, let's say I do מעילה,
Me'ila, I go on a little ride on top of my sheep
or something, okay, I scratch my back on it, I get some
benefit from it. Because the thing is seen as intrinsically sanctified, it
defines its identity, a simple misuse does not make it lose its
קדושה. Kedusha. If I've got a, okay, however, if something is only
קדושת דמים, Kedushat Damim, its only value is because it's waiting to
be sold and the proceeds to be used, the קדושה Kedusha doesn't
define it to the same degree, right? It's more like owned by
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It's not about its identity to the
same degree. So if I sanctified my car and the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash is going to just sell it and use the proceeds,
whether or whether I sanctified it so that the money goes to
upkeep or because I'm going to use the proceeds to buy an
עולה, Ola, whatever I'm going to do, but it's not about the
identity of the car. The car is just waiting to be sold.
So in that type of a case, if I do מעילה, Me'ila,
I actually in a way take it out of the ownership of
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It's more like stealing and it's more
easy for the קדושה Kedusha to go away because it's not as
intrinsic to it. Okay, is that clear? So two criteria for מעילה.
Me'ila. Number one is that something only something can as a result
of מעילה Me'ila something goes out of הקדש Hekdesh only in a
case of שוגג, Shogeg, not a case of מזיד, Mezid, which is
ironic, but that's the הלכה. Halacha. Number two is primarily it only
happens in a case of קדושת דמים, Kedushat Damim, not of קדושת
הגוף. Kedushat HaGuf. Only when it's about its value. When it's a
קדושה Kedusha about its identity, like then it does not lose it
even when it's been violated. So now we're talking about a pile
of money, and here's the argument. Maybe since this pile of money
is only קדושת דמים, Kedushat Damim, not קדושת הגוף, Kedushat HaGuf, okay,
and since were I to violate its status בשוגג, Be'shogeg, what would
be the effect? If I were to violate its status בשוגג, Be'shogeg,
misuse it בשוגג, Be'shogeg, it would be מעילה Me'ila and the קדושה
Kedusha would go away. So that proves that when you're dealing with
money as opposed to when you're dealing with the animal, you know,
its identity its status is a little bit more fungible, right? Its
status is less permanent because there are ways in which the קדושה
Kedusha could go away if I misused it in a particular way.
So maybe if I consciously, not בשוגג, Be'shogeg, consciously reassign it, maybe
that can work. Okay? It wouldn't be מעילה Me'ila because it would
be במזיד. Be'mezid. But since in a case of מעילה בשוגג Me'ila
be'shogeg you see that the קדושה Kedusha can go away, so maybe
that shows you that the קדושה Kedusha is less permanent to this
money, its identity is less permanently fixed, and therefore maybe it's possible
to reassign. And that's why we're suggesting that at least money for
a חטאת Chatat can be reassigned to another חטאת. Chatat. So let's
just read that in תוספות. Tosafot. הכי גרסינן שאין מעל וכיפר שהמעות
אין בהם קדושת הגוף, Hachi garshinan she'ein mo'al ve'chiper she'hame'ot ein bahem
kedushat haguf, the money as opposed to the animals is not intrinsically
sanctified. Okay? דחזי למיפק לחולין על ידי מעילה, Dehazi lemifak lechulin al
yedei me'ila, they would more easily lose their קדושה, Kedusha, it's less
permanent about its identity. וכשמשנה אותו לקרבן אחר נפיק המעות לחולין, Ucheshemeshaneh
oto lekorban acher nafik hame'ot lechulin,
and when you switch it to another, if you try to sort
of take that money to use for a different קרבן, Korban, you
would have done מעילה Me'ila and the money would have gone out
to be a non-sanctified, right? דהוין חולין ביד מוכר בהמה, Dahaveyan chulin
beyad mocher behemah,
and then you basically use that money and you gave it to
the guy to buy for a different type of a קרבן, Korban,
giving it to the sheep seller, right, to the shepherd or whatever,
that would have been an act of מעילה Me'ila and then the
money would have lost its sanctity because you would have misused it.
דלא נפיק לחולין אלא מועל Dela nafik lechulin ela mo'al ולכך נמי
כיפר בשוגג. Ulechach nami kiper be'shogeg.
Okay,
so therefore if it were שוגג Shogeg you actually would successfully be
able to reassign it because the act of having used it בשוגג
Be'shogeg would have been an act of מעילה Me'ila would have made
the money lose its קדושה Kedusha so you would have actually succeeded
to have reassigned the money. You would have violated, but you would
have succeeded because that would have been מעילה. Me'ila. ולכך נמי במזיד
נמי נימא דכיפר. U'lechach nami b'meizid nami neima d'kipher.
So therefore even maybe intentionally you can reassign the money, הואיל ושייך
בו שינוי בשוגג. ho'il v'shayeich bo shinui b'shogeg.
Okay, since when you did it accidentally, and by and therefore you
did מעילה, me'ila, it can get reassigned, it can change its status.
So maybe that shows that its status is more flexible, and maybe
therefore it's possible to even consciously and willfully reassign its status. Okay,
so that's a very complicated way, an interesting way though of demonstrating
that the קדושה kedusha of money is less fully about permanently defining
its identity than the קדושה kedusha of the animal that you're going
to bring as a sacrifice. So since therefore, I mean, you could
have had other ways of demonstrating it too. You know if an
animal you're going to use as a sacrifice, you can't transfer the
קדושה kedusha off unless the animal has a blemish. Money that you
sanctified you can transfer the קדושה kedusha off. So but through this
example of מעילה בשוגג, me'ila b'shogeg, it shows that that קדושה kedusha
is less permanent to the identity of the money and therefore maybe
I can even willfully reassign that money because to a different type
of a חטאת. chatat. Let's just finish this as the end of
the ברייתא. braita. So finally, this is the last thing we're trying
to suggest. A money that I sanctified for one sin, maybe I
can reassign to another sin offering for myself. Right?
All of it is a question.
All right, so now we're going to have to see the answer.
Okay, שהרי אבל. sheharei aval. Where was it? מנלן שכן אם הפריש
לעצמו מעות מן החלב והביא על הדם, על הדם והביא על החלב
שהן מעל וכיפר. Mnalan? Shekein im hifrish l'atzmo ma'ot min hachelev vehevi
al hadam, al hadam vehevi al hachelev shehein ma'al vekipher. תלמוד לומר:
Talmud lomar: על חטאתו. al chatato.
Nope. על חטאתו al chatato
is reinforcing the idea very specific to the person and to the
sin. Even if we're just dealing with money. עד שיהא קרבנו לשם
חטאתו. ad sheyei korbano l'sheim chatato. That the, it has to be
yours for your sin, whether it's animals and even if it's money,
it can only be for the thing that it is designated for.
Here's the קרא kera that a חטאת's chatat identity is totally fixed
on the person and on the sin. Michael does ask an interesting
question. I set it aside for one type of a חלב, cheilev,
can I use it for another? It would be more even more
interesting if I sinned twice, okay, before I separated it. Meaning, if
I sinned after I separated it, that's an easier to answer. But
let's say I went ahead and on Sunday I ate חלב cheilev
by mistake and on Monday I ate חלב cheilev by mistake, and
on Tuesday I set it aside for my Sunday sin. Okay, can
I then go ahead and bring it for my Monday sin? I
don't know, that's an interesting question. דב, Dov, you had a question?
Yes, I did. If he has this קדושת דמים kedushat damim for,
I mean it's מעילה בשוגג, me'ila b'shogeg, so in effect you're erasing
its identity because it's a type of a שינוי. shinui. Exactly. So
is that the same type of concept as in a regular case
of גניבה gneiva where I make a שינוי shinui and I gain
ownership at some point over the stolen object? Its identity changes?
Yeah, except by גניבה gneiva you have to actually physically change it
or, you know,
whereas here, it would make a change...
Exactly, exactly. Whereas here the very act of גניבה gneiva itself, or
גזילה gezeila or misuse or whatever, is itself enough of a שינוי
shinui to take, to have the קדושה kedusha go away.
So it's quality of שינוי.
shinui. Exactly, exactly.
It's similar,
I mean similar idea of שינוי רשות shinui reshut and there are
some גמרות gemarot that discuss because שינוי מעשה, shinui ma'aseh, שינוי הגוף
shinui haguf is not, that's a physical change. But there is ideas
when you can take possession of some object you stole when it
goes not to the hand of the גנב ganav but to a
third party's possession or whatever. So there is a sometimes a sense
when changing of possession makes the separates it from the original owner.
So there is some parallel, and there are גמרות gemarot that discuss
issues around יאוש ye'ush and שינוי רשות shinui reshut and compare it
to some מעילה me'ila cases, yeah.
I just wanted to ask about the, about this ברייתא. braita. Would
you say that this ברייתא braita style is much more like מדרש
הלכה? midrash halacha?
Totally מדרש הלכה. midrash halacha. I assume that it's, I mean I
didn't check, but I assume it's straight from the מדרש הלכה midrash
halacha on this פסוק.
pasuk. Because for something to be introduced as a ברייתא braita which
is so much like מדרש הלכה... midrash halacha...
No, the גמרא Gemara treats the ברייתות braitot the same. The גמרא
Gemara does not signal whether it's a מדרש הלכה midrash halacha or
whether it's a תוספתא Tosefta or whatever. Right. But very often you're
right, you see by the style it's clearly דרשן'ing darshen a פסוק,
pasuk, it's totally focused on that פסוק, pasuk, yeah.
So all this is by עולות, olot, I mean by חטאות. chataot.
Let's say, let's say it was like an עולה, ola, like you
know, what are you going to... like so what is that? Like
let's say the father had an עולה... ola...
Yeah, the son definitely can bring it,
then we have no restrictions at all, whether it be money or...
Correct, it can be brought though whether a person is יוצא as
somebody basically says I take upon myself an obligation to bring an
עולה ola and then the father leaves aside money, then the son
can't, then the he does, you know, he's not sort of יוצא
with money that's already been sanctified. Well actually it's interesting. No, I
don't think so. The general הלכה halacha is that it has to
בא מן... ba min... it can't be בא מן החיוב, ba min
hachiyuv, it has to be בא מן הרשות. ba min hareshut. But
anyway, I'd have to see if there's some cases where that could
work. But the basic point is in that case, the קרבן korban
can be brought but it doesn't go to fulfill the חיוב. chiyuv.
And in that way you're right that חטאת chatat might not be
here as distinctive as we're suggesting because there are two questions here:
one is can I use somebody else's קרבן... korban... or my own
קרבן Korban for purpose X to fulfill a different obligation, right? And
there might be, and there really is generally a rule, if you
have an obligation, you can only bring it from non-already obligated funds,
you know, you can only so you can't use something that went
for that was intended earmarked for different obligation for this obligation. That's
the general rule, so in that way חטאת Chatas is not so
distinctive. The greater distinctiveness of the חטאת Chatas is that is that
you know if used for the wrong purpose it's an invalid קרבן,
Korban, it can't be eaten, it has to be burned, all those
things, whereas other things, my, you know, a person's father's עולה Ola
or שלמים Shlamim or whatever is still brought, it doesn't satisfy the
person's obligation, but it's still brought. So you are right, there are
two points going on here. Yes.
This is another example where you have a long somewhat confusing סוגיא
Sugya that ends with a ברייתא Braitah that seems to explain things
much more.
Well, this ברייתא Braitah doesn't explain the issues that we were focused
on. This actually gives some fills in some background. We had been
referring to the special status of a חטאת Chatas that had not
been the focus of the discussion. And now we're actually to the
summary of this because what's the whole purpose is a great ברייתא
Braitah about the iden- about this clear idea of your sin, your,
you know, yours, this specific sin and so on. What's its relevance
here? So the whole relevance here was to get to this question
about animals that have been sanctified and non-specified and have a blemish,
are they like this pile of money that can be reassigned or
not? Right? Remember when the נזיר Nazir dies or when the נזירות
Nezirus gets annulled now what does this have to do with any
of that? Because you'll remember in the beginning of the ברייתא Braitah
when it discussed the possibility of a guy using his father's money,
it said well maybe money is more flexible because money by the
case of a נזיר Nazir the money can get reuse, you know,
he can use his father's unassigned money, right? Remember that in the
beginning of the ברייתא Braitah when it's trying to discuss how money
might be a little bit more flexible? So that's what we're going
to focus on. So that's the whole reason of quoting this. Let's
take a look at the end. So it says like this.
קתני מיהא. Katani Miha. So that was a great ברייתא Braitah but
the whole reason we brought that in was for the one of
the lines at the beginning where it says בהמה Behemah that it
says that it basically contrasts that you can't- a guy can't reuse
his father's animal for נזירות Nezirus but he can reuse his father's
money for נזירות. Nezirus. So when it said he can't reuse his
father's animal for
נזירות, Nezirus, מאי לאו אפילו בעלת מום? Mai Lav Afilu Ba'alas Mum?
Presumably that means even if the father sanctified animals with blemishes in
a non-specified way that that would be in the non-money category and
it cannot be reassigned. So don't you see that that means that
animals even with blemishes are not in the money category? So the
גמרא Gemara says לא תמימה. Lo Temimah. No, no, no. When we
said animals of the father cannot be reassigned by נזירות Nezirus that
was when it was the right animals, specified without a blemish. Those
are the things that can't be reassigned, but maybe everything else, right,
can be reassigned when we talk about this pile of unused funds.
So the גמרא Gemara says אבל בעלת מום מאי? Aval Ba'alas Mum
Mai? So what do you want to say? You want to say
if you're dealing with animals with blemishes and they're not the right
animals and they're non-specified that that is something that if the father
left that behind it can be reassigned in a case of נזירות?
Nezirus? כסתומא דמיא? Kistuma Damya? You want to say that's like something
unspecified? מאי איריא דקתני מעות שהפריש אביו? Mai Irya De-Katani Maos She-Hifrish
Aviv? Why is it focused, why is this case given as money,
that money is the case that can be reassigned? ליתני בעלת מום.
Lisni Ba'alas Mum. Give cases that aren't money. Talk about animals with
blemishes, other types of things, beams of wood. Why only mention money?
So the answer is obvious. הכי נמי. Hakhi Nami. You're right. That's
at least what it's talking about. דלמאי חזיא? De-Lamai Khazya? Because anything
that is not the animal itself that's going to be used as
a sacrifice, whether it's cash, whether it's animals with blemishes, whether it's
cars, whether it's beams of wood, if it's not the animal itself
that's going to be used as a sacrifice, it's all the same.
It's just stuff that's going to be sold for the ultimate purpose.
What is everything else fit for? לדמי? Lidmai? For the proceeds. דמי
הני מאות? Demei Hani Maos? So that's the same as the pile
of money. So all of this big discussion was because as the
גמרא Gemara often does it has the problem about the excluded middle,
right? Everyone knows the excluded middle like Aristotle said, right? There's, you
know, if in the universe of A and not A there's no
excluded middle because everything is either A or not A. Okay, I
mean, whatever, I'm sure I think current math says otherwise, but we
won't worry about that. Okay. Now the problem is that
the משניות Mishnayot often don't talk about a world of A and
not A. They talk about- they don't talk about chocolate and not
chocolate. They talk about chocolate and vanilla and make you wonder about
everything that's neither chocolate nor vanilla. All the the excluded middle, right,
coffee, exactly. So anyway, so here's the problem. We when we've been
talking about this money left over by this נזיר Nazir who died
or the woman whose נזירות Nezirus was annulled and unspecified funds get
to be used as an עולה Ola or in this or this
other parallel case unspecified funds by a father get to be used
by the son for his נזירות, Nezirus, okay, we contrast two extremes.
A pile of unspecified funds, that gets to be reused as an
עולה Ola or reused by the son. son for his נזירות nezirus
and animals that have been specifically or money that has been specifically
and concretely sanctified, this is the חטאת, chatas, this is the עולה,
olah, this is the שלמים. shelamim. Well there's a lot of things
that are not a pile of money or, you know, very concretely
different animals or different piles that have been specified for their purpose.
Like beams of wood, or animals with blemishes, that are the wrong
animals, or, you know, a million other things. So that's the question,
which category does it fall in? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is
trying to argue, well since it says animals and then maybe that
means that anything that's an animal falls into that animal category. And
the answer is no, anything that basically is not the thing itself
that's going to be used falls into the money category because everything
else is essentially about selling it and using the proceeds. So the
fact that it mentioned animals doesn't mean that it includes all animals.
It was only talking about the very specific animals that were going
to be used themselves. Okay, so the bottom line is the גמרא
Gemara ends with the sense that this idea of a pile of
money pretty much includes everything with the one exception of the animals
themselves that have been sanctified for use for their קרבן korban themselves
or different piles of money that this is a pile of the
חטאת, chatas, this is the עולה, olah, but, you know, when it's
very concretely and specifically has been sanctified for that specific purpose. But
if it's unspecified whatever the object is, cash, money, wood, you know,
anything, that would be the stuff that can be either reused as
an עולה olah or reused by the son for his, you know,
the money that the father left over.
And the גמרא Gemara is saying מעות maos represents that entire exactly.
Alright, so that was a long time on that סוגיא sugya and
finally we're going to start a new סוגיא. sugya. But yes, Jenna.
I think the logic is that like I feel like it's just
as likely that it would have said if it meant, you know,
the beams of wood, then it would have said it, right? And
the גמרא Gemara does that sometimes too. So it just gets to
arbitrarily decide whether it wants to
exactly, whether it assumes בהמה behema means, right, every type of בהמה
behema or exactly, yeah. You know, but it was an opportunity to
explore the topic. In many cases you wonder, you know, how much
did the גמרא Gemara not know the answer and was really discussing
and trying to derive it and how much was it just trying
to use this as an opportunity to flesh things out. And in
this case in particular maybe it was using this as an opportunity
to bring in this very nice ברייתא braisa to give us clarity
about why חטאת chatas is different. Like, I do a little bit
suspect that. That the purpose of bringing this last ברייתא braisa was
less to prove its case and more because this ברייתא braisa helps
give us greater clarity about the whole larger discussion.
It's interesting, I mean, because there might be an underlying idea that
the identity of an object, there is no such thing as generic
identity, it must have specificity in order for it to have an
identity that then cannot be transferred to something else. If it's unspecified,
its identity is
afloat at its value and the value can then gain an identity
in some, you know what I'm saying?
You lost me a little bit, but let's leave that for another
time. Let's start now the next משנה. mishna. Okay, so we still
have one last משנה mishna about the woman whose vows are being
annulled and now it's being annulled at a very inopportune time. So
we had talked about it being annulled, what happens with the money
that she had already sanctified or the animals she had already sanctified,
but things could have gotten even further along than just sanctifying the
animals. You could have actually slaughtered the animals and been in the
process of bringing them as a קרבן korban and then the husband
wakes up and he annuls the vows, right, as the קרבנות korbanos
are being brought, as the נזירות nezirus is ending. So let's take
a look. So נזרק עליה אחד מן הדמים, nizrak aleha echad min
hadamim, on the woman the blood of one of the sacrifices has
been sprinkled for her behalf, so one of the קרבנות korbanos has
already been brought, and then the husband says, oh, I want to
annul the vow. Okay, אינו יכול להפר, eino yachol lehafer, he cannot
annul it. Now why not? So the reason the גמרא Gemara is
going to give is not just because, you know, hey buddy, like,
you know, you're messing up a process here. No, the reason is
because after one of the animals has been brought, the assumption is
that her basically her restrictions of נזירות nezirus are over. She still
has the obligation of the rest, but her restrictions are over. Since
her restrictions are over, he no longer has the power to annul
because he could only annul the נזירות nezirus because it fell into
that category of, if you remember, the husband can only annul things
that are either ענוי נפש, inuy nefesh, considered to be things that
cause some affliction of the soul for the woman or somehow interfere
with their relationship. Well at this stage it does neither, right, when
a woman can't drink wine, that's ענוי נפש, inuy nefesh, okay. The
fact that she can't become טמא למת tameh lemeis or has to
grow her hair long is not considered to affect their relationship, although
one might ask about we'll see in a minute the hair growing
long, like is that supposed to be nice or is that supposed
to be unruly. Anyway, but the point is now that basically everything
is done and she's out free from the restrictions, he has no
longer any footing, any basis to annul the vow. Now it would
be interesting because the question would be what about a father and
his daughter, right? Here we're only exploring husband and wife. According to
some ראשונים, rishonim, a father does not have the same restrictions. A
father can... And categorically annul all of his daughter's vows regardless of
the nature of the vow. So that might be actually different. Okay.
But here we're dealing with husband and wife and once she's no
longer bound by those restrictions because one קרבן korban has been brought,
he no longer has an ability to annul the vow.
I'm missing a really simple piece. Yeah. I thought the הפרה hafarah
needed to be when he heard it like...
Yes, but he heard it the day that she brought it. He
was away on a trip, she went ahead and she made this
נזירה, nezirah, okay? She has a right, she has her own animals
to use, or he said to her, I don't know if you
ever need to bring any animals, don't hesitate, use stuff from my
flock. And then he comes back from his trip and his wife
leaves a note, I'll be back at three, I'm at the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And he goes to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and he says, what the heck is going on? And she says,
well, I was a נזירה nezirah the last 30 days when you
were away. So now it's יום שמוע, Yom Shmoa, that's the day
that... that's the day that he heard, yeah.
And that was obvious this whole time?
Yeah, of course. No, it wasn't obvious. Thank you for spelling it
out. All of this, when he does it, it means that he
heard, it's not when she took the vow, it's when he found
out about it.
He didn't know for 30 days.
He was off on a trip.
He, I don't know,
he thought she was pregnant. Every time he offered wine, she said
no thanks, he thought she was pregnant. I don't know.
Anyway, I'm just growing my hair long. Do you like it, right?
Okay. I mean, it's true, you can grow your hair long and
you can grow your hair long and not drink wine and not
go into a cemetery without it looking so different. It's only for
30 days. I'm serious. We think about a נזיר, Nazir, it's so
obvious. How obvious is it? It's only 30
days. You need
that much hair to grow? All right,
anyway. All
right, moving on everybody. All right, everybody, behave, behave. All right. נזרק
עליה אחד מן הדמים אינו יכול להפר. Nizrak aleha echad min hadamim
eino yachol lehafer. רבי עקיבא אומר אפילו נשחטה עליה אחת מכל הבהמה,
Rabbi Akiva omer afilu nishchata aleha achas mikol habehemah, even before the
blood's been sprinkled, even after the animal... one animal has been slaughtered,
אינו יכול להפר, eino yachol lehafer, he cannot. Now why not? Because
after the animal's been slaughtered, she still is restricted in drinking wine
until the blood is thrown. So for the next two minutes, it's
still a category of a vow that he could annul. So why
can't he annul it after slaughtering before the blood's been sprinkled? Because
the... it's not yet been offered as a sacrifice and she's still
bound by the restrictions. So the basic reason is what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say is because of הפסד קדשים, hefsed kodshim,
because... because... I'm sorry, you're being distracting, okay, so sit please. Because
of הפסד קדשים, hefsed kodshim, which is that if he annuls it,
right, as soon as... if he annuls it, let's say we're talking
about the חטאת, Chatas, which the גמרא's Gemara going to say we're
talking about the חטאת. Chatas. So if he annuls it before the
animal was slaughtered, what would you do with the חטאת? Chatas? You'd
have to let it die, right? That we know. But here... so
if he annuls it after the blood's been sprinkled, it was already
brought validly. Let's say he annuls it after the animal's been slaughtered
before the blood's been sprinkled. So the blood can't be sprinkled now
because you no longer have a נזיר Nazir who's obligated in a
חטאת, Chatas, so you have a dead animal with blood which is
now you can't use. You have to take it all and just
burn it. Okay, so you basically have to waste the whole thing.
You have to interrupt this whole process and waste the whole thing
if you annul it at this stage before the blood has been
sprinkled. So that's a concern of הפסד קדשים. hefsed kodshim. Now it's
not exactly clear to me, you could say הפסד קדשים hefsed kodshim
is even if he would have annulled it two weeks ago. Once
the animal's been sanctified, we learned it has to be let to
die. But here, A, it's an interrupting of a whole process, there's
something a little bit different about like at the verge of bringing
it and we're interrupting the process, we have to take it out,
we have to burn it, and so on. And number two is
the benefit is trivial. It's he only benefits like what for one
minute, to save you that one minute of her not drinking wine
anyway. What's she going to do, drink wine in the בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash? You know, so the benefit is so trivial and it's
going to lead to throwing out the whole קרבן korban that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says we're not going to let you do it
for that. Now תוספות Tosafos asks an interesting question. Very nice you're
going to tell me you're not going to let me do it
for that. Let's say I ignore you and I go and I
do it anyway and I annul the vow anyway. Would the annulment
work? Would we say יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה
yesh koach beyad chachamim la'akor davar min haTorah that we are going
to somehow void your annulment? Even though biblically you could annul, by
policy reason we don't want you to annul now, it's a waste
of a קרבן, korban, and we're going to void it. Or are
we going to say no, בדיעבד bedieved if you did it, it
would work, but we're not letting you do it. Okay, so that's
an interesting question תוספות Tosafos doesn't know the answer to. But that's
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva idea. For God's sake, there's only one minute
left of the vow, we're not going to let the guy annul
it at this stage. Yes.
How would he even... I mean, it's he's presumably not with her
or he would have known earlier, right? So he's somewhere, how's he
going to get a messenger?
No, he showed up at the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Hey hon,
what are you doing? Oh, didn't you know I've been a נזירה
nezirah for the last month? Uh-huh. What? I annul that vow! I
don't care the animals are already slaughtered, I'm annulling it! What?
Dramatic end of the movie where he like...
Exactly, exactly, exactly, like catching her in the airport before the plane
takes off. Exactly. Okay. So, all right.
Okay, anyway. Okay. המצוה המנויה בתגלחת הטהרה. HaMitzvah HaMenuya BeTiglachat HaTahara.
That's when she's ending—she's about to shave and she's ending the נזירות
Nezirut at the end of a normal process, בתגלחת הטהרה. be-tiglachat ha-tahara.
אבל בתגלחת הטומאה, aval be-tiglachat ha-tuma,
if she's bringing קרבנות korbanot and she was טמאה, teme'ah, יפה, yafeh,
then even if like the חטאת chatat has already been slaughtered and
the blood hasn't been sprinkled and it's exactly the same scenario in
that case, or even after the blood's been sprinkled, according to תנא
קמא, Tanna Kamma, in that case, you can always annul. Why? שהוא
יכול לומר shehu yachol lomar
because he can say, אי אפשי באשה מנוולת, ee efshi b'isha menuvelat,
I don't want a wife that is going to be disfigured or,
you know, by having her hair grow wild. That's again interesting, the
hair growing long says something about מנוולת. menuvelat. You don't really have
to say אי אפשי אשה מנוולת. ee efshi isha menuvelat. What you're
really saying is she's got another month of נזירות nezirut left. So
it doesn't matter if the sacrifices have already been brought. The only
reason it mattered that the sacrifices have already been brought was because
then the נזירות nezirut was over and there was—he no longer had
any—any standing to annul the vow. Okay, but it's הפסד קדשים hefsed
kodashim if she hasn't been bringing any קרבן. korban. You sanctify the
money and then the husband annuls. That was the last—that was the
last משנה. Mishna. The reason of הפסד קדשים hefsed kodashim was if
all you benefited was—was one minute. Okay, here, we're basically—there's a full
month of the נזירות nezirut left. It doesn't matter what stage you
are in bringing the קרבנות. korbanot. There's a month of the נזירות
nezirut left. You're allowed to annul. Okay, that's that case.
Okay. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, some have it רבי, Rebbi, אומר, omer,
אף בתגלחת הטהרה יפה, af be-tiglachat ha-tahara yafeh, שהוא יכול לומר אי
אפשי באשה מגולחת. shehu yachol lomar ee efshi b'isha megulachat.
So he says like this: I disagree with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said—I disagree with תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma said after some of the blood has been sprinkled.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said even before it's been sprinkled when the
animal's been slaughtered. I say up until the last minute you can
annul. Maybe even if all three animals have been offered, you can
annul. Why? What's the benefit of your annulling at that last minute?
If I annul the vow at the last minute, then she doesn't
have to do that last stage that ends the נזירות, nezirut, which
is shaving her hair. So I don't want her to shave her
hair. I don't want a bald wife. So therefore, I'm going to—even
after everything has been done, I'm going to go ahead and annul
it at the last minute because I have a right to—to not
want her to do that last stage. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. מתניתין דלא כרבי אליעזר. Matnitin d'la k'Rabbi
Eliezer. Our משנה Mishna is not like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דאי
רבי אליעזר, de-ee Rabbi Eliezer, הא אמר תגלחת מעכבת. ha amar tiglachat
me-akevet. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that the shaving holds back releasing
from the restrictions of נזירות. nezirut. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, of course it wouldn't be enough to have brought one sacrifice.
You'd be allowed to annul until everything had happened, right? Because up
through the shaving because the—the restrictions are still there, right? So our
משנה Mishna says after the first sacrifice the husband can't annul because
then she's no longer held by the restrictions. So that's not like
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say that he
could annul up through the end because she's bound by the restrictions
to the end.
So he's like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right?
It is not the same as רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says the reason he can annul is because even though
she's not bound by the restrictions, he has a right to prevent
her to shave. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is from a different perspective.
Since she is bound by the restrictions until she shaves, he has
a right to annul because of the restrictions. Okay? So you're right.
Both of them go up through shaving, but from a different perspective.
Okay. וכיון דלא גילח אסירה בחמר. V'keivan d'lo gilach asira b'chamar. As
long as she hasn't shaved, according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, she's
prohibited in wine. וכיון דאית לה ניוול, v'keivan d'it lah nivul, and
since it's some type of—not physical disfiguring, but some type of affliction,
it's something that impacts her, and therefore that's עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh,
that's the category of things the husband can annul, מצי מפר, matzi
meifer, he can annul. Okay, so the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
you can't annul after the first קרבן korban because the restrictions aren't—she's
not bound by them. But according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you
can annul up through the end because she's bound by the restrictions
up through the end. תנא קמא דידן סבר, Tanna Kamma didan savar,
our תנא Tanna holds, כיון דאזרק עלה דם לאלתר שריא בחמרא, keivan
d'izrak ala dam l'alter sharya b'chamra, once the blood of one sacrifice
has been brought, she's immediately permissible with wine. ולית לה ניוול, v'leit
lah nivul, and it's no longer—again, a funny use of the word
ניוול, nivul, but it's not something that's like an עינוי נפש, inuy
nefesh, afflicts her, impacts her, and therefore the husband does not have
a right to annul it. So therefore he says once one sacrifice
has been brought, you have no longer any standing to annul. רבי
עקיבא סבר, Rabbi Akiva savar, אפילו אשתחטה בהמה, afilu ishtachata behema, even
once the animal has been slaughtered, even though she's still bound by
the restrictions for one more minute, אינו יכול להפר, eino yachol l'hafer,
he can't annul משום הפסד קדשים. mishum hefsed kodashim. It's true she's
still bound by the restrictions. It's still—he still has standing to annul
because there's one more minute left of the restrictions, but we're not
going to let him annul. To get out of that one minute
of restrictions, we're not going to let you take the whole קרבן
korban and—and throw it away and burn it and burn it. Okay,
it's too big of a loss for too little of a gain.
So that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, now. מתקיף לה רבי זירא.
Matkif lah Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira asks, ואמאי וליזרוק דמן
שלא לשמן וישתרי בחמרא. v'amai v'lizrok daman shelo lishaman v'yishtarei b'chamra. For
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva now I've been telling you that the problem
is that we're dealing with the חטאת chatas for
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and חטאת chatas right if it stops being
a נזיר nazir after slaughtered before the blood, so you can't sprinkle
the blood because it's a חטאת chatas that no longer is the
חטאת chatas of a נזיר. nazir. The woman stopped being a נזיר.
nazir. Okay but the גמרא Gemara doesn't yet realize that it's a
חטאת chatas and I jumped to the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara assumes it's talking about any of the animals,
even the עולה olah and the שלמים. shelamim. So the גמרא Gemara
says big deal, let you've שחט shechted the עולה, olah, now she's
no longer a נזיר, nazir, so still go ahead and bring the
עולה. olah. It'll be like an עולה olah brought for the wrong
purpose which still is כשר. kosher. So it's an עולה olah which
started off as an עולת נזיר, olas nazir, it's being brought by
the end, the blood is being sprinkled for a non-עולת נזיר olas
nazir purpose because she's not a נזיר. nazir. Fine, an עולה olah
brought for the wrong purpose is still a כשר קרבן. kasher korban.
You don't have to destroy the קרבן, korban, you can still eat
the meat. Okay, like we've been saying before, when the נזיר, nazir,
it's a, when the נזיר nazir dies or when her status is
annulled earlier, you get to re, you can use the עולה, olah,
the animal sanctified for an עולה, olah, for a free-will עולה. olah.
So the same here, what's the loss according to רבי עקיבא? Rebbi
Akiva? Sprinkle the blood, it'll still be a כשר קרבן. kasher korban.
Okay. So רישא דאמרת שלא לשמה. Risha damat shelo lishman. שלא לשמה
Shelo lishman doesn't mean you have to intentionally think I'm doing this
for something other than an עולה. olah. It means by virtue of
the fact that she's no longer a נזיר, nazir, it's by definition
not לשמן. lishman. Its identity was עולת נזירה, olas nezira, now she
after it's been slaughtered she's not a נזיר, nazir, so the blood
is going to be sprinkled not for the purpose of an עולת
נזירה, olas nezira, by definition is שלא לשמה shelo lishman because she's
no longer a נזיר. nazir. But nevertheless even though it's being brought
for not its right purpose, its identified purpose, it's still
כשר. kosher. Okay. וייתי בשר באכילה, ve-yatei basar ba-achilah, the meat will
be permissible. מי לא תניא? Mi lo tanyo? We taught in a
ברייתא: Baraita:
כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret, the lambs that are brought for the, for
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem on שבועות, Shavuot, ששחטן שלא לשמן, she-shachtan
shelo lishaman, if they were slaughtered for not for the right purpose,
או ששחטן לפני זמנן או אחר זמנן, o she-shachtan lifnei zamnan o
achar zamnan, or they were slaughtered before or after שבועות, Shavuot, הדם
יזרק ובשר יאכל, hadam yizarek ve-basar ye-achel, the, the, you sprinkle the
blood and you eat the meat. ואם הייתה שבת, Ve-im hayetah Shabbat,
but if it was שבת, Shabbat, so you, because normal, if it
was being done for the right purpose you bring the קרבן korban
of שבועות Shavuot on שבת, Shabbat, but now that it was done
for the wrong purpose, it was שחט shechted for something else in
mind, you can't go ahead and offer it on שבת. Shabbat. So
what do you do? לא יזרק, Lo yizarek, don't sprinkle the blood.
ואם זרק הורצה, Ve-im zarak hurtzah, but if you did then it's
כשר. kosher. להקטיר אימורין לערב, Le-haktir imurin la-erev, but don't bring the
אימורין imurin on שבת Shabbat itself, you bring them that night, because
obviously you can't burn the אימורין imurin on שבת Shabbat itself. Anyway,
the relevance is that if we even though it's brought שלא לשמה,
shelo lishman, it's still כשר. kosher. Now of course תוספות Tosafot says
why did you have to bring this weird ברייתא Baraita about lambs
of שבועות? Shavuot? You know there's a general הלכה halacha that all
קרבנות korbanot other than a חטאת chatas that are brought שלא לשמה,
shelo lishman, the meat is still כשר. kosher. So one answer that
I would suggest is that the case of שבועות Shavuot is interesting
because parallel to שלא לשמה, shelo lishman, שלא לשמה shelo lishman is
intentionally you're thinking the wrong thing. I'm שחט shechting these lambs of
שבועות Shavuot and I'm thinking I don't know what it is, I'm
thinking that it's an עולה. olah. Okay but the, but the, this
is interesting because it also has cases where you might be thinking
the right thing but it's the wrong time. If you brought it
before שבועות Shavuot or after שבועות, Shavuot, that's also defined as שלא
לשמה. shelo lishman. Here it's similar. The guy might be thinking the
right thing, but by definition it's the wrong time. The woman's no
longer a נזיר, nazir, so it's not exactly the wrong time, but
you know the wrong context. And that itself is a type of
a שלא לשמה. shelo lishman. It's brought in a way in which
it cannot be serving its intended purpose and nevertheless it's still כשר.
kosher. Okay, so not such a big deal. It was an עולה,
olah, it was a שלמים, shelamim, it can't be used for its
intended purpose, but it's still כשר. kosher. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says so what's the answer? So אמרי, amri, אי דשחט עולה או
שלמים, i de-shachat olah o shelamim, if we're talking about the עולה
olah or שלמים shelamim הכא נמי, hacha nami, then רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva wouldn't have a problem. Go ahead and הפר annul the, the
נזירות nezirus and finish bringing the עולה olah and the שלמים. shelamim.
Why not? אבל הכא במאי עסקינן, Aval hacha be-mai askinan, what's the
case? כגון ששחט חטאת ברישא. Kegon she-shachat chatas be-reisha. We're talking about
the חטאת chatas was the first one that was שחט. shechted. כי
דתניא: Ki de-tany: גילח על אחת משלשתן יצא. gilach al achat mishaloshan
yatza. Any one of the three ends the נזירות. nezirus. So רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva when he said if you if you שחט shechted
one and you haven't sprinkled the blood and it's only one, because
the נזירות nezirus is still in effect, like that's the case תנא
קמא Tana Kamma says you can הפר. annul. When it's only the
first animal's been שחט, shechted, so the נזירות nezirus has been in
effect but the blood hasn't been thrown. So רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
says if that first animal was a חטאת, chatas, okay yes, as
soon as you sprinkle the blood the נזירות nezirus will end, but
since the, and therefore the תנא קמא Tana Kamma says you can
do a הפרה hafara now, I'm going to say you can't do
a הפרה hafara now, because the חטאת chatas would have to go
to waste. That's when the first animal is a חטאת. chatas. If
the first animal was an עולה olah or שלמים shelamim רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva would agree you could הפר annul it because then eventually
you could just go ahead and bring the animal anyway. Let's just
finish to the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, במה דברים אמורים, bameh devarim amurim,
בתגלחת טהרה, be-tiglachas taharah, ובתגלחת טומאה יפר. ve-tiglachas tumah yafer. If it's
a טמי טומאה tamei tumah you can because then ultimately there's a
month to go so of course the husband can still הפר. annul.
ורבי מאיר אומר, ve-Rebbi Meir omer, we'll skip the parenthesis, אפילו בתגלחת
טהרה יפר, afilu be-tiglachas taharah yafer, מפני שיכול לומר אי אפשי באשה
מנוולת. mipnei she-yachol lomar i efshi be-ishah menulachas.
מאיר *Meir* says, even until the last minute of a normal טהרה
*taharah* process, even all three animals have been brought, he can be
מיפר *meifer* before the shaving because he can say I don't want
her to go through the process of shaving. Okay, so that's so
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says up to the last minute he can
be מיפר *meifer*. So what's the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*? The תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma* אמר לך *amar lecha*, אפשר בפאה נכרית *efshar bepei
anachris*, just have her wear a wig. Okay, so how can you
say that's not a legitimate complaint that you don't want a wife
with a shaved head? She can always wear a wig. רבי מאיר
סבר *Rabbi Meir savar*, and רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* holds, דפאה נכרית
איידי דזוהמא לא ניחא ליה *depei anachris adi dezuama lo nicha lei*.
No, if some other foreign hair or wig, it has some, it
has smell. It doesn't smell natural. It's not her smell. So therefore
he can say I don't like her wearing a wig. And therefore
he says he can still annul. So we will end on that
lovely.